<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Maiesties message to both Houses of Parliament; brought from the Isle of Wight upon Mouday [sic] the fourteenth of August 1648. By the right honourable, the Earle of Middlesex, Sir John Hipsley, and Master Bunckley concerning the personall treaty.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78897</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864475</idno>
  <idno type="VID">162094</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240902347</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2460A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E458_11*</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205031</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864475</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99864475e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78897)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162094)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 73:E458[11*])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Maiesties message to both Houses of Parliament; brought from the Isle of Wight upon Mouday [sic] the fourteenth of August 1648. By the right honourable, the Earle of Middlesex, Sir John Hipsley, and Master Bunckley concerning the personall treaty.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare. 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:162094:1"/>
            <p>HIS MAIESTIES Message To both Houses of Parliament;</p>
            <p>Brought from the Isle of WIGHT upon Mouday the fourteenth of August 1648.</p>
            <p>By the Right Honourable, the Earle of Middlesex, Sir <hi>Iohn Hipsley,</hi> and Master <hi>Bunckley</hi> concerning the Personall Treaty.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q xml:lang="frm">DI<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>V ET MON DROIT</q>
               <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <figDesc>royal blazon surmounted by a crown and flanked by the English lion and Tudor rose on one side and the Scottish unicorn and thistle on the other</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="King_to_Parliament">
            <pb facs="tcp:162094:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:162094:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>CARISBROOKE <date>Aug. 10. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the peace of my Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were not much dearer to me than any particular interest whatsoever, I had too much reason to take notice of the severall Votes which passed against Me, and the sad condition I have bin in now above these seven moneths; But since you, my two Houses of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, have opened (as it seemes to me) a faire beginning to a happy Peace, I shall heartily apply my selfe thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and to that end I will as clearly and shortly as I may, set you downe those things which I conceive necessary to this blessed worke; so that we together
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:162094:3"/>may remove all impediments that may hinder a happy conclusion of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which with all cheerfulnesse I em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace.</p>
            <p>And to this wished end your selves have laid most excellent grounds; for what can I reasonably expect more than to treat with Honour, Freedom &amp; Safety, upon such propositions as you have, or shall present unto Me, and such as I shall make to you. But withall remember that it is the definition not names of things, which make them rightly knowne; and that without means to performe no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position can take effect: and truly my present condition is such, that I can no more treat, than a blinde man judge of colours, or one run a race who hath both his feet fast tyed together; wherefore my first necessary demand is, That yee would recall all such Votes and Orders by which people are frighted from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, writing, or speaking freely to Me; next, that such men of all professions whom I shall send for as of necessary use
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:162094:3"/>to me in this Treaty may be admitted to wait upon me. In a word, that I may be in the same state of freedome I was in when I was last at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed lesse cannot in any reasonable measure make good those offers which you have made me by your Votes; for how can I treat with Honour as long as people are terrified by Votes, and order to come, speak, or write to me, and am I honorably treated so long as there is none about me except a Barber, who now came with the Commissioners that I ever named to wait upon me: or with freedom untill I may call such unto me, of whose services I shall have use in so great and difficult worke: and for Safety (I speake not of my Person having no apprehension that way,) how can I judge to make a safe and well grounded Peace, untill I may know without disguise the true present state of all my Dominions, and particularly of all those whose interests are necessarily concerned in the Peace of these King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:162094:4"/>which leades me naturally to the last necessary demand, I shall make for the bringing of this Treatie to a happy end, which is.</p>
            <p>That I alone, or you and I joyntly; doe invite the Scots to send some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons authorized by them, to Treat upon such Propositions as they shall make, for certainly, the publique and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary interest they have in this great set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telement, is so clearely plaine to all the world that I beleeve no body will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the necessity of their concurrence in order to a durable Peace, wherefore I will onely say, that as I am a King of both Nations, so I will yeeld to none in either Kingdome for being truly and zealously affected, for the good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of both, my resolution being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be partiall for either, to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the other. Now as to the place, because I conceive it to be rather a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstantiall then reall part of this Treatie, I shall not much insist upon it, I name <hi>Newport</hi> in this Isle, yet the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:162094:4"/>zeale I have that a speedy end be put to these unhappy distractions, doth move me earnesty to desire you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fider what a great losse of time it will be to Treat so farre from the body of my two Houses, when every small debate of which, doubtlesse there will be may ny, must be transmitted to <hi>Westminster</hi> before it be concluded.</p>
            <p>And really I thinke, though to some it may seeme a Parodox, that peoples minds will be much more apt to settle, seeing me Treat in or neare <hi>London,</hi> then in this Isle, because so long as I am here, it will never be believed by many, that I am so really free, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Treatie begin I expect to be: and so I leave and recommend this point to your serious consideration. And thus I have not onely fully accepted of the Treatie, which you have proposed to me, by your votes of the third of this moneth; but also given it all the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance that lyes in me, by demanding the necessary meanes for the effectuall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:162094:5"/>performance thereof, all which is so ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily implyed by, though not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulary mentioned in your Votes, as I can no waies doubt of your ready complyance with me herein, I have now no more to say but to conjure you by all that is deare to Christians, honest menor good Patriots, that yee will make all the expedition possible to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin this happy worke, by hasting down your Commissioners, fully authorized and well instructed, and by inabling me (as I have shewed you) to Treat pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the God of Peace so to blesse our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, that all my Dominions may speedily enjoy a safe well grounded Peace.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Charles R.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>For the Speaker of the Lords House pro tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore, to be communicated to the Lords and Commons in the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> at <hi>Westminster.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>